Socialist Labor Party Records on Microfilm 5168 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Socialist Labor Party Records on Microfilm
1877-1906
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Socialist Labor Party
State Historical Society of Wisconsin
5168 mf
4.33 cubic feet
39 microfilm reels
Records (documents), microfilm.
Consist of the official records of the Socialist Labor Party from its organization in 1877 until 1907. Despite the fragmentation or paucity of some types of records, the collection as a whole documents many facets of the Party's development, organization, thought, and tactics, as well as its contribution to the labor and socialist movements in a turbulent era of industrial change and of social and economic stress in the United States.
3834156
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, January 23, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1877, the Socialist Labor Party (SLP) developed into the foremost socialist organization in the United States at the turn of the century and was the first American Marxist party to maintain its existence over a long span of years.
In 1877, the Workingmen's Party of the United States reorganized and changed its name to Sozialistische Arbeiter-Partei or, in its English version, the Socialistic Labor Party, a title which, fifteen years later, was changed to Socialist Labor Party. Of the estimated 90% of the members of foreign origin, Germans formed the most numerous nationality group and furnished many of the leaders, although the first secretary, Philip Van Patten, was a native-born American. A great deal of the material in this collection is in German.
Throughout its early decades the Socialist Labor Party was frequently torn by internal factional disputes and controversies. One group of militant unionists, led by F.A. Sorge, withdrew in 1877-1878. Two other factions, sydicalist and anarchist in tendency, led by Albert Parsons, August Spies, and Johann Most, withdrew in 1881. Within the remaining membership conflicts were waged between Lassalleans, the right-wing members committed to political action, and the Marxists, the left-wing revolutionary members emphasizing militant unionism. The Lassalleans controlled the Party until 1889, but in the 1890's, through the influence of new leaders, including Daniel De Leon, Hugo Vogt, Lucien Sanial, and Henry Kuhn, the Party developed an aggressive program emphasizng both militant trade unionism and independent politcal action.
In 1895, the SLP broke off relations with the American Federation of Labor and formed the Socialist Trade and Labor Alliance. It was never able to mount any serious challenge to the AFL, and its remnants joined in founding the Industrial Workers of the World in 1905.
The SLP fielded its first national ticket in 1892 and did so again in 1896. In state and local politics, particularly in New York State, the Party provided numerous candidates beginning in 1877, although it sometimes supported progressive or populist candidates running under other party labels. In 1898, the Party had reached the zenith of its size and influence, with an estimated membership of 6,000 and 82,000 votes garnered for its own candidates in state and local elections.
Dissatisfaction with Party policies and leaders persisted among members friendly to the AFL, members evolutionary in their concept of socialism and members who resented De Leon's autocratic personality and Party discipline. Led by Morris Hillquit, many of these dissenters withdrew in 1899 to form the Socialist Party, and from this schism the SLP never fully recovered. Following the withdrawal of Hillquit and the death of De Leon in 1914, the SLP's principal activity was educational agitation.
Scope and Contents
Records of the National Executive Committee include one volume of minutes (1889-1891) in German; five volumes of outgoing correspondence (1883-1892), primarly in German and English, with some letters in French, largely concerning routine Party business and including an inventory of letters received (1891-1894), which in turn includes a list of Sections organized and dissolved between 1891 and 1893, with notations on their nationality; incoming correspondence chiefly addressed to national secretary Henry Kuhn (1878-1906, bulk 1895-1899), much of which pertains to the mechanics of Party operations and includes discussion of Party philosophy and strategy, internal Party controversies, campaigns and elections -- the campaign of 1896 is particularly well documented -- Board of Appeals cases, strikes, publications, and editorial policies of the party press, organization and operation of the Socialist Trade and Labor Alliance, other labor organizations, agitation tours, national conventions, international affiliations, and Party finances; official ballots of the SLP Sections and the members at large on assorted questions of party policy and selection of party officials (1880, 1889-1904); official accounting records of the Committee (1881-1899); an agitators' date book (1896) containing itineraries of SLP agitators and candidates during the 1896 presidential campaign; and a list of Sections nad officers, ca. 1896.
Records of the party press (1885-1904) pertain to the official newspapers owned by the Party as well as to other socialist-oriented newspapers which at times endorsed and advocated the principles of ths SLP. The nature of the files varies between publications, but includes some correspondence, lists of subscribers, accounts, and minutes. The Party-owned enterprises represented include the New York Labor News Company and the Workamen's Printing Company, which handled publication and distribution of Party pamphlets; Der Sozialist and its successor, Vorwarts, a German weekly edited by Hugo Vogt; The People, official Party weekly in English, begun in 1891 with Daniel De Leon as editor; the Daily People Committee, organized in 1895 to raise money for a daily newspaper in English which was issued and edited by De Leon from 1900 to 1914; and the Abendblatt, a daily published in Yiddish. Also included in this series are files relating to two papers outside Party ownership, the Arbeiter Zeitung and the New Yorker Zeitung.
Records of the National Board of Appeals (1878-1900) (known as the National Board of Supervision between 1877 and 1896) concerns disciplinary action aken against Sections and members and includes official minutes (1879, 1899-1900); a letter book (1878-1880) in German and English; correspondence (1888-1899, 1893, 1895-1900), containing letters in German and Enlgish between the Board and Party officials and members, affidavits and testimony, and reports of the Board to the national conventions.
Records of the National Conventions (1877-1904) include printed plarforms, constitutions and proceedings for most years for which there are files, as well as some correspondence, reports and resolutions for some years. The Conventions were called by a vote of the Party membership and met irregularly. Portions of the files are in German.
Records concerning Party activities (1880-1905) include two notebooks kept by Party leaders W.L. Rosenberg and Daniel De Leon, and an assortment of newspaper clippings, mainly from socialist publications. Clippings pertain to the labor and socialist movements, and particularly to the activities of the SLP, including its debates, conventions, party philosophy, agitation and speaking tours and political campaigns.
The records of State Committees and Local Sections (1878-1906) complete the collection. Massachusetts, New York, Texas, Washington, and British Columbia are represented through records of Local Sections of American, German, Flemish, Italian and Scandinavian membership. There are also incomplete files of minutes and correspondence of the New York State Committee within the period 1884-1902. Fragmentary as it is, this series does illustrate the varied international composition of the Party membership and the organization and operation of the Party on the state and local levels.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Electioneering--United States.; Labor -- United States -- Political activity; Political parties -- United States -- Discipline; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1896; Press, Political party -- United States; Press, Socialist -- Unied States; Socialism.; Socialist parties -- United States; Socialists -- British Columbia -- Vancouver; Socialists -- Massachusetts -- Adams; Socialists -- Massachusetts -- Boston; Socialists -- New York (State) -- New York; Socialists -- New York (State) -- Buffalo; Socialists -- New York (State) -- Mount Vernon; Socialists -- New York (State) -- Newtown; Socialists -- Texas -- Houston; Socialists -- Washington -- Everett; Labor unions -- United States -- Political activity; Scrapbooks; Socialist propaganda -- United States; New York Labor News Company; Socialist Labor Party; Socialist Trade and Labor Alliance; Workmen's Printing Company; Historical Society of Wisconsin; De Leon, Daniel, 1852-1914.; Ham, F. Gerald, 1930-; Hintze, William; Kuhn, Henry; Rosenberg, W. L.
3834156
- Vol. 1: Minutes, 1889-1891; 1 (Reel 1)
  Scope and Contents
  1889 August 28-1891 September 27.
- Vol. 2: Letter Book, Outgoing Correspondence., 1883-1885; 2 (Reel 1)
  1883 June 20 - 1885 June 5.
- Vol. 3: Letter Book, Outgoing Correspondence., 1888-1889 (Reel 2)
  1888 August 14 - 1889 June 4.
- Vol. 4: Letter Book, Outgoing Correspondence., 1889-1891 (Reel 3)
  1889 June 4-1891 May 26.
- Vol. 5: Letter Book, Outgoing Correspondence., 1891-1892; 1 (Reel 4)
  1891 June 6-1892 March 25.
- Vol. 6: Letter Book, Outgoing Correspondence., 1892; 2 (Reel 4)
  1892 March 26 - December 27.
- Vol. 7: List of Letters Received., 1891-1893; 3 (Reel 4)
  1891 October 16-1893 June 23.
- Vol. 8: List of Letters Received., 1893-1894; 4 (Reel 4)
  1893 June 23-1894 October 9.
- Vol. 9: List of Letters Received., 1897-1899; 1 (Reel 5)
  1897 January 20 -1899 May 10.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1878-1885; 2 (Reel 5)
  1878 - 1885 January 19.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1885-1895 (Reel 6)
  1885 January 20-1895.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1896 (Reel 7)
  1896 January-June.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1896 (Reel 8)
  1896 July-August.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1896 (Reel 9)
  1896 September.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1896 (Reel 10)
  1896 October.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1896 (Reel 11)
  1896 November-December.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1897 (Reel 12)
  1897 January-March 18.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1897 (Reel 13)
  1897 March 19 - May.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1897 (Reel 14)
  1897 June-July.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1897 (Reel 15)
  1897 August - September.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1897 (Reel 16)
  1897 October-November.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1897 (Reel 17)
  1897 December - 1898 January.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1898 (Reel 18)
  1898 February - April.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1898 (Reel 19)
  1898 May - June.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1898 (Reel 20)
  1898 July-August.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1898 (Reel 21)
  1898 September - October.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1898 (Reel 22)
  1898 November-December.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1899 (Reel 23)
  1899 January - March 22.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1899 (Reel 24)
  1899 March 23 - May 22.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1899 (Reel 25)
  1899 May 23 - December.
- Incoming Correspondence., 1900-1906; 1 (Reel 26)
  and undated.
- Ballots, 1880-1900; 2 (Reel 26)
  1880, 1899-1900.
- Ballots, 1901-1904 (Reel 27)
- Vol. 10: Account Book, 1881-1885; 1 (Reel 28)
  1881 November 17-1885 January 31
- Vol. 11: Account Book, 1884-1888; 2 (Reel 28)
  1884 January 1-1888 February 6
- Vol. 12: Account Book, 1888-1890; 3 (Reel 28)
  1888 October 17-1890 November 7
- Vol. 13: Account Book, 1890-1891; 4 (Reel 28)
  1890 November 8-1891 August 21
- Vol. 14: Deutsche Reichstagswahl Account Book, 1884; 5 (Reel 28)
  1884 April 20 - December 31
- Account Book. Money Orders, 1886-1888; 6 (Reel 28)
  1886 October 30-1888 March 16
- Account Book. Special Funds, 1893-1896; 7 (Reel 28)
  1893 January 17 - 1896 July 17
- Account Book. Dead Debts, 1895-1899; 8 (Reel 28)
- Vol. 15: Agitators' Date Book, 1896; 9 (Reel 28)
  1896 August 1 - November 1
- Vol. 16: List of Sections and Officers, 1896; 10 (Reel 28)
- Vol. 17: New York Labor News Company, Letter Book, 1889; 11 (Reel 28)
  1889 April 9 - August 21
- New York Labor News Company, Orders for Books, 1904; 12 (Reel 28)
  1904 May 24 - July 30
- Vol. 18: Der Sozialist, List of Subscribers, 1885-1891; 13 (Reel 28)
- Der Sozialist, News Dealers' Accounts, 1889-1891; 14 (Reel 28)
  1889 July 1-1891 April 2
- Vol. 19: Arbeiter Zeitung, Account Book, 1898-1899; 15 (Reel 28)
  1898 May 2-1899 July 29
- New Yorker Volkzeitung and Vorwarts, Correspondence, 1889-1895; 16 (Reel 28)
  1889, 1891-1895
- New Yorker Volkzeitung and Vorwarts, Correspondence, 1896-1899 (Reel 29)
  and undated
- Correspondence., 1892-1895 (Reel 30)
  1892, 1894 - 1895 October.
- Correspondence., 1895-1896 (Reel 31)
  1895 November - 1896 October.
- Correspondence., 1896-1897 (Reel 32)
  1896 November - 1897 September.
- Correspondence., 1897-1901 (Reel 33)
  1897 October - 1901, undated.
- Daily People Committee. Minutes., 1895-1899; 1 (Reel 34)
  1895 February 13- 1899. December 3.
- Abendblatt. Minutes., 1901; 2 (Reel 34)
  1901 October 21.
- Abendblatt Fund. List of Subscribers., 1900-1901; 3 (Reel 34)
  1900-1901 [ ?].
- Workmen's Printing Company. Records., 1901-1902; 4 (Reel 34)
  1901 May 14-1902 April 15.
- Workmen's Printing Company. Minutes., 1879; 5 (Reel 34)
  1879, November 8 - December 1.
- Workmen's Printing Company. Minutes., 1899-1900; 6 (Reel 34)
  1899 August 16 - 1900 May 27.
- Workmen's Printing Company. Letter Book., 1878-1880; 7 (Reel 34)
  Vol. 20. 1878 April 1-1880 April 20.
- Workmen's Printing Company. Correspondence., 1888-1900; 8 (Reel 34)
  1888 - 1889, 1893, 1895-1900
- 1877 Convention, 1 (Reel 35)
  platform, constitution, resolutions, and proceedings.
- 1880 Convention, 2 (Reel 35)
  platforms, constitutions, resolutions, and proceedings.
- 1881 Convention, 3 (Reel 35)
  platform and constitution.
- 1883 Convention, 4 (Reel 35)
  platforms, constitution, and proceedings.
- 1885 Convention, 5 (Reel 35)
  platforms, constitutions, and proceedings.
- 1887 Convention, 6 (Reel 35)
- 1889 Convention, 7 (Reel 35)
  platforms, constitutions, proceedings, report, correspondence, credentials, and votes.
- 1893 Convention, 8 (Reel 35)
  platforms, constitutions, reports, correspondence, and credentials.
- 1896 Convention, 9 (Reel 35)
  platforms, constitutions, proceedings, reports, correspondence, credentials, and votes.
- 1900 Convention, 10 (Reel 35)
  constitution and proceedings.
- 1900 Convention (continued), 1 (Reel 36)
  proceedings (continued) and correspondence.
- 1904 Convention, 2 (Reel 36)
  constitution, proceedings, reports, resolutions, and correspondence.
- W. L. Rosenberg. Notebook., 1884; 3 (Reel 36)
- Daniel De Leon. Notebook., 1896-1897; 4 (Reel 36)
  1896 January 2-1897 January 2.
- Scrapbook I, 1880-1898; 5 (Reel 36)
- Scrapbook II, 1880-1905; 6 (Reel 36)
- Scrapbook III, 1892-1897; 7 (Reel 36)
- Scrapbook IV ( Moritz Ruther Scrapbook), 1886-1900; 8 (Reel 36)
- Scrapbook V (Fred W. Long Scrapbook), 1894-1900; 9 (Reel 36)
- Clippings, 1880-1903; 10 (Reel 36)
  1880, 1889-1890. 1892, 1894-1901, 1903, undated.
- Adams Section. Minutes., 1884-1886; 1 (Reel 37)
  Vol. 21. 1884 November 23-1886 June 13.
- Adams Section. Minutes., 1886-1888; 2 (Reel 37)
  Vol. 22. 1886 July 30-1888 October 2.
- Adams Section. Minutes., 1886-1890; 3 (Reel 37)
  Vol. 23. 1886 April 15-1890 September 18.
- Adams Section. Minutes., 1895-1897; 4 (Reel 37)
  Vol. 24. 1895 July 10-1897 September 29.
- Adams Section. Account Book., 1885-1897; 5 (Reel 37)
  Vol. 25. 1885 December - 1897 November.
- Adams Section. Dues Book., 1885-1896; 6 (Reel 37)
  Vol. 26. 1885 January - 1896 December.
- Boston, Flemish Section, Dues Book., 1892-1894; 7 (Reel 37)
  Vol. 27. 1892-1894 September.
- Boston, Scandinavian Section. Minutes., 1904-1905; 8 (Reel 37)
  Vol. 28. 1904 March 31-1905 March 16.
- New York State Committee. Minutes., 1896-1901; 9 (Reel 37)
  Vol. 29. 1896 August 23 -1901 November 11.
- New York State Committee. Minutes., 1899; 10 (Reel 37)
  1899 April 28.
- New York State Committee. Correspondence., 1884-1895; 11 (Reel 37)
  1884-1885, 1894-1895.
- New York State Committee, Correspondence., 1896-1902; 1 (Reel 38)
  1896-1902. undated.
- Buffalo Section. Branch 2 (llth Ward), Minutes., 1899-1901; 2 (Reel 38)
  Vol. 30. 1899 June 10-1901 April 13.
- Mount Vernon Section, Minutes., 1894-1898; 3 (Reel 38)
  Vol. 31. 1894 April 29-1898 August 20.
- Mount Vernon Section. Account Book., 1894-1898; 4 (Reel 38)
  Vol. 32. 1894 June 2-1898 August 20.
- Mount Vernon Section. Dues Book., 1894-1898; 5 (Reel 38)
  Vol. 33. 1894 May 5-1898 July.
- New York City Central Committee, Minutes., 1879; 6 (Reel 38)
  Vol. 34. 1879 April 25-October 25.
- New York City, American Section. Minutes., 1878-1879; 1 (Reel 39)
  Vol. 35. 1878 January 3 - 1879 October 15.
- Newtown Section, Ridgewood-Glendale Branch, Minutes., 1889-1891; 2 (Reel 39)
  Vol. 36. 1889 May 19-1891 October 24.
- Newtown Section. Ridgewood Branch, Account Book., 1889-1891; 3 (Reel 39)
  Vol. 37. 1889 May -1891 October.
- Houston. Italian Section. Minutes., 1896-1898; 4 (Reel 39)
  Vol. 38. 1896 February 22-1898 May 9.
- Houston. Italian Section. Dues Book., 1896-1898; 5 (Reel 39)
  Vol. 39. 1896 February - 1898 April.
- Everett Section. Minutes., 1897-1898; 6 (Reel 39)
  Vol. 40. 1897 October 1-1898 April 7.
- Vancouver. Socialist Trade and Labor Alliance, Local Alliance No. 250, Minutes., 1899-1900; 7 (Reel 39)
  Vol. 41. 1899 June 4- 1900 December 21.
- Vancouver. Socialist Trade and Labor Alliance, Local Alliance No. 250, Account Book., 1899-1900; 8 (Reel 39)
  Vol. 42. 1899 June 4-1900 December 23.